<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mrs. James's vindication of the Church of England in an answer to a pamphlet entituled A new test of the Church of England's loyalty.</title>
            <author>James, Elinor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36027</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15586958</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15586958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1150:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mrs. James's vindication of the Church of England in an answer to a pamphlet entituled A new test of the Church of England's loyalty.</title>
                  <author>James, Elinor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for me, Elinor James,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>New test of the Church of England's loyalty.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>JAMES</hi>'s VINDICATION OF THE Church of England, IN AN ANSWER TO A PAMPHLET ENTITULED, A New Teſt OF THE Church of England's LOYALTY.</p>
            <p>It is not Intereſt that moves me to this, for I never made Gain of any thing that ever I did, nor none I do deſire; for it was nothing but the Fear of Gods Judgments that hath been the ſole Cauſe of all my Actions for above theſe Twenty years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for me <hi>Elinor James.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103998:2"/>
            <head>An Advice to the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS for Conſcience, I do not count it a ſufficient Guide, becauſe it is not ſo Infallible, but it is ſubject to Err, and therefore it ought to be Guided by the Word of God; for I find thoſe that will not be Guided by that, doth not yield Civil Obedience to Temporal Magiſtrates, and how can they to God: And therefore I am not ſo much for Liberty of Conſcience. But ſince it is the Kings Pleaſure, I reſt ſatisfied; for if they miſimploy it, is not Gods Hand long enough to reach them? But who knows but that God that Converted St. <hi>Paul,</hi> may Convert them all that are Zealous and did not intend any thing elſe but His Glory; but for thoſe that are Envious, you muſt not look that they will ever be otherwiſe. I know they offended you, becauſe they pretend to be Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Indeed I wonder how they dare ſay ſo, when the World knows they never had any! But why ſhould any be unwilling to return the King Thanks, I think it is no more than what every one is obliged to; and ſince the King was pleaſed to Renew His Promiſes, that none need to doubt his Fidelity; I think it is but Reaſon to renew your Thanks. And as for <hi>Oxford,</hi> they are no Example, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none lies under their Circumſtances; but when His Majeſty is pleaſed to remove their Doubts, I don't queſtion but that they will be forward enough with their Addreſſing, and 'till that be done, I cannot blame them; but I find you ſcruple, becauſe you will not be after the Diſſenters, what a ſimple Pride is that? For a Chriſtian ought to Imitate all Good Things, and therefore there is no Excuſe. Fear not any thing, but Truſt in God, Love the King, and be Kind one to another, and do not Addict your ſelves to any thing but what is Agreeable to Chriſtianity. And I think you are obliged to frequent the Prayers of the Church, for Chriſt did it, and how much more ought we. I am very ambitious that you ſhould exceed others, I have always Loved the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would have them to be Dignified above all; and that the Love of God ſhould be the Mover of all their Actions.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> though ſome blame him for uſing my Name, I do not; becauſe he hath uſed it civilly. Indeed I do not know him, nor never read his Book, but I am told that he doth Abuſe the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> for which I blame him: For I count it not Wiſdom for a Wit, to Reflect on that he ſo lately own'd.</p>
            <p>I hear there are Queries Cried, but I have not ſeen them, but underſtand they are of the ſame Nature. O that I were but a Man, I would ſtudy Night and Day, and I do not doubt but I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould be more than a Conquerer, and ſo I hope to be nevertheleſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103998:2"/>
            <head>Mrs. <hi>JAMES</hi>'s VINDICATION OF THE CHURCH of ENGLAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am very ſorry to think that you ſhould be always ſuch a Subtle Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but you ſay, You never had an Opportunity to ſhew your Spite and Malice until now. You ſay you could never find a <hi>Convincing Reaſon,</hi> and what was the Cauſe? Is it not becauſe it doth not conſiſt with your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; for that is all that you aim at, for that is the God of this World, and he hath blinded your Eys, and ſtupified your Underſtanding, and thickens your Scall, ſo that if an Angel came to Inſtruct you, you would not be able to receive it, if it did not agree with your Intereſt. I thought <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> might have chang'd your Diſpoſition, ſeeing that the Kings Intention is ſo Gracious, as thinking it is the beſt way to Unite our Differences, and to heal our Breaches, and you know it was the Care of the King and Parliament, to prevent Scandalous Pamphlets againſt the King and Government, and therefore it is ſtrange to me how you can Print your Paper <hi>with Allowance, when it is of ſuch a Pernicious Nature, and its whole Aim is againſt the Government:</hi> ſurely thoſe Gentlemen that had the Care of the Government, are very Negligent, or elſe you dare not ſay, <hi>With Allowance;</hi> certainly none that is in Authority would grant it you, and if they did, they muſt be Treacherous to their Truſt, and are no Friend to the King and Government: for can there be any thing of a more Pernicious Conſequence than this, <hi>that would deſtroy the very Foundation? How do you think I can bear it,</hi> when God hath fill'd my Heart full of Love and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and I know you Abuſe them, for you have no cauſe to call their Loyalty into queſtion, for I know <hi>Their Loyalty, and have been a Labourer with Them,</hi> therefore I have the greater Reaſon to Plead for them: but I know you will ſay <hi>I am a Woman, and why ſhould I trouble my ſelf?</hi> Why was I not always ſo, when I pleaded with the Parliament about the <hi>Right of Succeſſion,</hi> and with <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and elſewhere; and I made Applications to my late Soveraign Lord the King (whom my Soul Loved) <hi>That he would be pleas'd to let me Undertake for the City, and to make me a God Mother,</hi> to which the King Anſwered, <hi>It would be too great an Undertaking for me,</hi> but I replied, <hi>That if it might not be for all, that it might be for ſome,</hi> and the King granted my deſire, and I ask'd His Majeſty whether He would not wiſh Well to it, and the King Replied, <hi>Ay, with all my Heart and Soul:</hi> Was not he a Gracious Prince, for I am ſure He ſought nothing but the True Intereſt of His People, but I know ſuch as you, are none of His Friends, for you did all you could to <hi>Pervert his Kingdoms and Sow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iviſions amongſt his People,</hi> and (by ſuch Doings) <hi>you made his Throne Uneaſie.</hi> Indeed then you might be for the Dukes Intereſt, becauſe it was your own, but I am ſure it was His loſs, for before He looked toward you, all the People Lov'd and Admir'd Him: And who was the cauſe of the Change, was it not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103998:3"/>you, <hi>That went up and down Incenſing the People of the great Proſelites you had made</hi> (for I ſuppoſe you are a Prieſt, and they were of the ſame Nature) <hi>for they came to me, and I know what they ſaid;</hi> therefore I find ſuch as you are the Plotters, for they troubled me many Weeks together, and I thought I ſhould never get Rid of them, but I Faſted Seven Days and Nights to give the late King a Petition, that He might know in what State His Kingdom ſtood in, and though I never ſaw them afterwards, yet I do not queſtion but there was endeavours uſed to blind Him; but if it had pleaſed God, that His Majeſty had Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed a little longer, I do not doubt but he would have taken New Meaſures, <hi>That you ſhould never have had cauſe to Boaſt, that you made him a Preſelite:</hi> And as for my Soveraign that now is, he is as Sweet and Precious a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince as the World can afford, and it is pity you ſhould <hi>Abuſe Him,</hi> for He is a King of Great Experience, and hath Suffered as much as any Prince in the World, which doth teach His Majeſty ſuch Wiſdom, that it is His whole Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to keep His Kingdoms in Peace, and to have His People to Flouriſh, and will not diſturb the Peace thereof upon any Condition whatſoever, and (God be Thanked) the King hath no need to diſtruſt us, for is not His God our God, and we acknowledge Him to be a Chriſtian King, who Belives in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty who made the Heavens and the Earth, and he doth believe that Jeſus Chriſt is His Son, and that he came into the World to Save Sinners, and I doubt not but that His whole Truſt is in His Merits, and we all hold and own the ſame; ſo that we lack nothing but a Holy Life, agreeable to the Life of Jeſus; but I find you are Mettleſome Spirits and want Employ; therefore I would deſire you to go to the <hi>Turks and Infidels,</hi> and Convert them, and in ſo doing you might expect your Reward, and I ſhould like it well; but for you to think that you can Convert People when they are Converted already, is meer Nonſenſe; for it is Perverting, and undoing what the Bleſſed Spirit hath done, which will be a Sin of ſuch a Nature, that I would not be guilty of it for all the World. I know you will be Angry, but I do not value it, for I muſt diſcharge my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience toward all, <hi>and if you would have me to be your Friend, you muſt take New Meaſures,</hi> and Learn of Chriſt, <hi>for he did Good to all, and hurt to none; and if you would not have me to ſpeak againſt you, you muſt not give me the Occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure my Soveraign will not allow you to Villifie and Abuſe us; for He is a Prince of Juſtice as well as Mercy, and hath promis'd, <hi>That He will Defend us,</hi> and not only ſo, but will venture as far as any in our Vindication, and the King was ſatisfied with our Loyalty, and declared it to the World, and how dare you condemn the Kings Judgment, and Scandalize the Church; for all that knows Her, knows Her to be the only Church for Loyalty: for doth any of you own the King to be Supream Head and Governour but She? And for your part, all the World knows what you own; ſo that my Soveraign cannot be your Supream Governour, and therefore there is no Compariſon to be made, <hi>I my ſelf can Weigh you all down for Loyalty;</hi> and if I can do ſo much <hi>for</hi> that am but one, what ſhall we all do? Therefore I know the King will not be Angry with me if I Vindicate the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for in Vindicating of Her, I Vindicate His Majeſty, which I have always done; for when the Peers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103998:3"/>Speech Abuſed my Soveraign, I Anſwered it; for I hate Rebellion, and the Church doth not hinder any one from that Singular Gift of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, for Her Deſire is, <hi>That all ſhould Fear God and Honour the King;</hi> and She is the Spouſe of Chriſt, and He will own Her for His Myſtical Body, and <hi>every one that truly believes in Chriſt, is a Member of that Body, and all the Members makes the Whole, and Her Doctrine is Holy:</hi> I wiſh thoſe that own Her, would Live according to Her Doctrines, for then they would be Safe and Happy: <hi>She hath been Infallible in Her Duty to Her King,</hi> which Her Diſcontented Brethren knows full well, for that was the only thing that they laid to Her Charge, <hi>That She would not be Treacherous to Her Prince, nor Side with His Enemies;</hi> for if She had, you would not have been ſo great as you are now, tho She was not for Popery as ſome thought, for indeed <hi>She hath always been the Bulwark againſt it;</hi> and that makes you Envy Her ſo: for you think if you can but bring Her down, you ſhall do well enough with the Brats whom you Begot, tho your Infallible Belief in them may deceive you; for though you made them Enemies to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> find they will prove no Friends to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for indeed every Good Soul will rather endure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing than to be inſlaved with <hi>Popery:</hi> And as for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> She never Lived under the Slaviſh Fear of it, as the Diſſenters did, but doth Truſt God with all, and deſires nothing elſe but to Serve God Truly, and the King Rightly And as for <hi>Her Revelations,</hi> as you ſay <hi>is Peculiar to Her Self,</hi> is a clear Miſtake, and yet <hi>Her Lord and Head</hi> hath promiſed, <hi>That the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt Her:</hi> And what is the Gates of Hell? <hi>But all thoſe things that lead us to Darkneſs and Ignorance, and to fling down Gods Holy Will, and to ſet up the Will of Men, and ſecretly makes us to be an Enemy to Chriſt, and a Friend to <hi>Anti-Chriſt?</hi>
               </hi> But Chriſt is able to Save <hi>HIS OWN,</hi> and that you ſhall know, for He hath His Choſen People amongſt all, and I really do believe He hath His Saints and Servants in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as well as any other, and I hope (our of His Infinite Mercy) He will Reconcile our Differences, and make us Happy: And as for thoſe that envies our Happineſs, <hi>They ſhall not be able to ſtand before the Almighty in the Day of His Anger, for His Power is able to diſperſe them, and to blow them away in a Minute, as his Divine Power did the Locuſts.</hi> Therefore I would Adviſe all the Enemies of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to be Quiet and Amend for the time to come, for while we are Contriving the Ruin of one another, God may juſtly deſtroy us all, and bring in the Heathens, who may bring forth better Fruits than we: And for your <hi>Allowing our Loyalty to King</hi> Charles I. I do not thank you, for it is well known, or elſe you would not have owned it; <hi>For that Deſtruction of Three Kingdoms, and the Death of the Beſt of Princes, is Writ in Gods Book,</hi> and who ſhall be called to an Account for it, God Almighty knows, <hi>but I am ſure You cannot be Acquitted: For was it not the Fear of Popery, with your Pride, that cauſed the Difference, when you Compelled the Queen to go bare-foot, and in the mean time ſuch as you Rid in Her Coach; to the great Hazard of Her Life:</hi> For (as I was told) She Miſcarried; who did you learn it of, I am ſure not of Chriſt, nor His Diſciples: And for your <hi>Loyalty to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103998:4"/>King</hi> Charles I. was it not for your own Protection? For the wrath of God was ſo upon you for you Sins and Iniquities, that you might very well have the Fear of <hi>Cain</hi> upon you: And as for the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> what made it ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but becauſe we had Complied as near as we could to you for Unities ſake. <hi>And the Occaſion of the War, and of that Good Prince loſing His Life and Crown, might be (for ought I know) for Sheltering ſuch Unfortunate Men as you are,</hi> for you were not ſo Senſible nor ſo Honeſt as <hi>Jonah</hi> was, for he declared the Truth, That he was the Man that had Offended, and by his Counſel the Ship was Sav'd; but you are of a contrary Nature, for you do not care if you periſh your Selves, ſo others periſh with you; but the Saints and Servants of God are not of that Nature, as <hi>Abraham, Moſes, David,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt Himſelf;</hi> for He undertook Death that we might Live; and Poverty, that through Him we might be made Rich; but <hi>You are an Enemy, for you would have none Rich but your ſelves, thinking thereby to enſlave us and triumph over us.</hi> Therefore I find you have the Nature of <hi>Cain,</hi> who Envied his Brother, becauſe his own Deeds were Evil. For my part, I can call God to Witneſs I have been always for the Peace of the King and Kingdom, and there is nothing in the World that is dearer to me than the Kings Life and Happineſs; and if I had a Thouſand Lives, I could Sacrifice them all in Vindication of His Sacred Majeſty, without the hope of Rewards or Gain; and there is none of my Enemies can Object any thing againſt me, but being over Zealous for my Soveraign Lord: For my Bleſſed Saviour hath Taught me. <hi>That I cannot ſerve Two Maſters,</hi> and the Primitive Chriſtians were always olig'd to be for the Intereſt of the Prince in whoſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they Lived; ſo that it is our Chriſtian Duty to Love and Pray for our own Prince, but we have nothing to do with any other; and whoever is for the Intereſt of another, cannot be a True Subject to their own: Therefore my Reſolution i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, That I will be True to my God, my King, and my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and I am reſolv'd (by the Bleſſing of Almighty God) never to Change if I were to ſuffer a Thouſand Deaths, becauſe God hath Inſtructed me in that Way from my Infancy, and I find it moſt agreeable to the Word of God and my Temper, for I am naturally Inclin'd to Love Kingly Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hority: And as for <hi>my Faith, it is to Believe Sincerely in Chriſt, and there is no other Faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any one can be Saved; for I am ſure He is the Infallible Rock,</hi> and I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept to that from the beginning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d I hope I will continue ſo to the end: And as for <hi>The Changes of Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſhip,</hi> that is not any thing as to Matter of Faith, <hi>for Prayer may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to Peoples Occaſions,</hi> for they were never deſign'd to be Infa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> if the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> hath been Altered, I did not care if it had been Altered again, and again, rather than it ſhould be a ſtumbling Block to any (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here is not any thing but what I like and love) and I think <hi>There is no Good Chriſtian but may ſay</hi> Amen <hi>to them,</hi> and I could Wiſh our Hearts were as Holy as the Prayers are good, then I am ſure there is no Body would be weary of them: But hath not ſuch as you put the people out of Love with them, in ſaying, They came out of your <hi>Maſs Book,</hi> and this you did to Wound the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for Her Good Will towards you; but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103998:4"/>you may ſee how the people Love you, for they will not accept of any thing from you, tho never ſo good; and if they will not accept of that they may, I hope they will not accept of that which they may not: for if they do, they will not deſerve the name of Men, and how much leſs then, will they be worthy of the name of Chriſtians, <hi>for if they do not own Chriſt now, they ſhall not be own'd hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I wonder how you dare Condemn the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (I mean that part of it, which is for the <hi>King, Common Prayer</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi>) for Her Faith Teaches Her Piety to Her God, and Loyalty to Her Prince; therefore She may appropriate to Her Self alone, <hi>The Principles of True Loyalty</hi> above all; for Her Doctrine is True, and Exhorts all to Repentance and Good Works, and Teaches a True Faith in Chriſt, and doth not Judge any Hereticks that differs with Her, but owns that whoever truly believes in Chriſt and Works Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, may be in a State of Salvation: and She is Chriſts Beloved Spouſe, and He will own Her, and I doubt not but Her Faith is great enough (with Gods Help) to ſtand againſt all Her Oppoſers, for Chriſt will Beautifie Her for His Words ſake; for tho She doth not Teach us that Preſumption as to think that any Man is Infallible, yet She owns Gods Word to be Infallible, and Eternal, and a Perfect Guide to Salvation. I wonder how any one can be Her Enemy, but why ſhould I? Was it not ſo from the beginning, for was not <hi>Cain</hi> Envious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Abel,</hi> and was not brave and renowned Men in their Generations Enemies to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and did not the High Prieſts Plot againſt my Bleſſed Saviour? And did not Chriſt tell his Diſciples, <hi>That the time would come, that they ſhould think they did God good Service to deſtroy them?</hi> They were not Heathens that did it, but thoſe Miſtaken Chriſtians that thought they ſhould Merit by it; for I find all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long that Satan hath made uſe of thoſe that ought to be the greateſt Friends, to be the moſt Inveterate Enemies, <hi>as when he made uſe of a Diſciple to betray his Lord;</hi> and <hi>that great Diſciple</hi> that declar'd moſt Love to his Lord, was the firſt that diſown'd Him. This is the Spite of our Spiritual Adverſary; and the Wiſdom of God ſuffered it ſo to be, that we ſhould not Truſt in any thing, but in the moſt High God, that always takes care of them that Truſt in Him, and none can prevent the Providential care that God takes of His, and Chriſts Church muſt look to be Perſecuted by the Enemies of Her Lord, but through Him She ſhall be more than a Conquerer. Who is he that is ſo Preſumptions to Brand her with <hi>Killing of Kings?</hi> She Abhors ſuch Doctrines, for She is a Preſerver of Kings and Princes, and makes more of Her Word than the Enemies doth of their Infallible Promiſe, and I doubt not but it will paſs currant. <hi>Hath not you been Angry with her Kings for Her ſake, and for what Reaſon; only becauſe She owned the Word of God in Sincerity: And out of Envy you ſent Men to divide Her Members, and deſtroy Her Government, and have you not been Contriving Her Ruin all along, and Tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>forming your ſelves into all Shapes to bring it to paſs? And who begins all Quarrels but you?</hi> And do you ſay, <hi>That the Church is a Viper?</hi> No, no, it is ſuch as you are; for you envy our Happineſs, and would <hi>Hurry us into a Confuſion,</hi> becauſe you think the King Loves us too well,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103998:5"/>and ſtands in the gap to hinder <hi>Your Intentions,</hi> and is like an Angel to keep Peace amongſt us, that every Man ſhould Enjoy His Right and Property: But this is contrary to your Temper, for you long to Enjoy what other Men have; and therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> is the great Eye-ſore: And ſince the King hath been ſo Gracious to give <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> you think that all the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſhould be againſt the Church to Devour Her: but God knows it was for your ſakes that the Laws were put againſt <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and how many Good Souls was againſt it, but dare not ſpeak for fear of being counted <hi>Whiggs;</hi> but for my part, I made Application to the hate King, That the Laws ſhould not be put againſt them, not that I lov'd them ſo well, but I know their Nature, and don't delight that any ſhould be Afflicted; no, not the <hi>Roman Catholicks:</hi> but you intend well to Reward us; and for my late Soveraign you have Abuſed Him ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, but you got Money by it.</p>
            <p>Sir, I am ſorry for your Ignorance, that you ſhould think the <hi>Church</hi> was <hi>in Her Infancy in</hi> Edward VI. <hi>Time.</hi> It is a clear Miſtake, <hi>for She hath been ever ſince Man hath had a Being;</hi> and do not <hi>Deſpiſe King</hi> Edward, for he was a brave Prince, and I doubt not but that he is a Saint in Heaven; and methinks it is not Wiſdom in you to <hi>Lampoon upon the Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> becauſe it was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled in <hi>Thirty Nine Articles;</hi> for they will ſtand when you will fall: and for you to ſay, <hi>She <hi>Set up a Brat of Her own:</hi> Was it not the Kings deſire that it ſhould be ſo to Prevent Popery,</hi> and what harm would it have been for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> if it had been ſo? <hi>For her Reign was but Short and her Life full of Trouble,</hi> and tho ſhe ſent a great many to Heaven, ſhe will have no Reward for it; for ſhe might <hi>have been a Better Chriſtian, if ſhe had Let Them Alone:</hi> But why were <hi>They ſo End ous as to Burn the Bibles? For whoever Hateth that, is an Enemy to God:</hi> From ſuch the Lord Deliver my Soveraign and all Good Souls; And the Lord grant a Right Underſtanding, for what Miſchief hath been wrought for want of it: For Chriſt ſays, <hi>He is a Door and a Vine,</hi> and if any could not underſtand it, muſt they be put to Death. Who is the giver of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding but God? And to ſome it is not given that they ſhould underſtand the Myſteries of Heaven, and ſince it hath pleaſed God to give us a Right Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, why ſhould you be Angry? You had need to pray to God to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie your own Underſtanding;</hi> for there is not any thing more like the Devil than <hi>Envy:</hi> And how <hi>Deſtructive would you be if you had but Power,</hi> that you dare to lay the <hi>Death of Queen</hi> Mary <hi>at our Door,</hi> when you ought to have blamed the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> for hunting her out of her Kingdom; and if Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did Cut her off, what have we to do with that? Should the King be blam'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> was Rebellious; God forbid, for I am ſure my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign lov'd him ſo well, that he would have delighted to have made him Great and Happy, if he had not wrought his own Deſtruction by his Rebellion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let it be upon his own head, and to thoſe that Adviſed him to ſuch a wicked Thing: And for to <hi>Villifie Queen</hi> Elizabeth, is a thing I Abhor, for I hate any ſhould ſpeak Evil of any Body that is Dead, but how much more of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> And do not all know that King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. was lawfully Married to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103998:5"/>Her Mother, and if the <hi>Pope</hi> delayed the Divorce, it was no Fault of the King nor Kingdom; and did not <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> loſe his Head, becauſe he told <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> it was not lawful for him to take his Brothers Wife? Therefore how dare you to ſay, <hi>That the Queen was a Baſtard,</hi> when all the World knows it is a great Lie? <hi>For every Good Chriſtian ought to Love Her Memory, and you to Chuſei</hi> for if She had not denied her Self that bleſſed happineſs of Marriage, my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord had never been King; and therefore for <hi>His ſake as well as Her own, I ſhall always Love and Admire Her Memory:</hi> And if Gods Providence had not defeated the <hi>Powder Plot,</hi> my Precious Soveraign would not have had a being in this World, nor that which is to come. Therefore I will always Admire and Adore the God of Heaven, that doth prevent the <hi>Wicked Intentions of Evil Men.</hi> For how hath God preſerv'd His Anointed from the Spite and Malice of Men and Devils, and from the Raging of the Seas? And I hope He will <hi>Preſerve Him ſtill, that He may Glorifie Him,</hi> that neither Men nor Devils may prevent Him from doing His Liege Duty to God; for it is He alone hath Preſerv'd Him, and kept Him hitherto, and I hope He will for ever and ever: And that He may not forget who <hi>Deſtroyed His Grandfather,</hi> Henry IV. <hi>of</hi> France, <hi>For They are the Snakes that will ſting to Death:</hi> And for the <hi>LAWS,</hi> they ſhall ſtand to <hi>Whip ſuch as You,</hi> that would <hi>Deſtroy both King and Government.</hi> I know you would Unthrone my <hi>Soveraign,</hi> for to make your ſelves <hi>Lords and Princes ower us;</hi> but I hope God will never ſuffer it: for I know you are like the Wheadling Diſſenters, that would not Truſt the King with His own Power, but pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they would Employ it, and make Him a Glorious Prince; but it was to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Him: ſo <hi>You would Wheadle the Church to take away Her Power,</hi> and then you think to do well enough with my <hi>Soveraign,</hi> when you have got the Power, and then you'll ſhew your Loyalty: but I hope the King will keep His Power, and Truſt to none of you; for you will all prove Treacherous if you can but make any Advantage of it; for you cannot but know the ſinking Condition of your Kingdom, and that makes you ſo Buſie; therefore you don't care who ſinks, ſo you ſwim: But what is it that can hinder Gods Intentions, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Amendment of Life, for that is the Glory that God deſires; for that end Chriſt came into the World, that <hi>God might be All in All,</hi> and these is no doubt but God makes the Angels Miniſtring Spirits, but they cannot do any thing of themſelves, for they continually Wait upon the Almighty; for when He moves they flee, and what Injury can it be to you to pray to God that moves all Things? I think it is the greateſt Favour that can be given to Mortals, but you ſay, <hi>You are not Worthy;</hi> and pray what is the Reaſon of that? For did not <hi>Chriſt Die for all that would lay hold of Him?</hi> But I find you have not attain'd to that Excellent Perfection to have a True Faith in Chriſt, for if you had, you would never have brought your falſe Accuſations againſt us; for what do we do, that you find ſo much Fault with us? for I am ſure all Condemns us for doing ſo much. And as for the <hi>Diſſenting Parliament,</hi> I was as much againſt them as any, but I wondered that they did do no more, when the late King ſaid, <hi>He would E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Proteſtant Religion to the End of the World;</hi> but they were ſo Factions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103998:6"/>they could not agree; for there was a Duke ſtood in their Way; but did not we ſtand for Him, and overthrow all their Doings? And did not we value the Kings Life (that now is) above our own: We could not adhear to their fair Pretences, to do Evil that Good might come of it, neither to hurt Him in the leaſt, but Truſted God with all; and if He was a King (as He is) we would lie at His Mercy: And what made the Diſſenters to be ſo much againſt us, but becauſe we were ſo much for His Majeſty? And how dare any to Abuſe us? I have not Patience to bear it, for if I let it alone, the very ſtones would ſpeak in Vind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cation of U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And as for the <hi>Parliament</hi> that now is, it is a very <hi>Honeſt Parliament,</hi> and I Love them, and Wiſh them all Well, and they are Knaves and Fools that ſpeaks againſt them; for they have Eſtabliſhed the King in His Throne, and Bear down His Enemies, and have Supplied His Wants; And what is it We have not done for our Soveraign? For we Love Him above all things in this World, for we Acknowledge Him to be Chriſts Vice-gerent, and therefore we own none (for our Governour on Earth) but He; and I do not doubt but our Loyalty will out-doe all Upſtart Loyalty: for ours doth not proceed from <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> but it proceeds from God: Therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> needs not Change Her Loyalty, neither will the King doubt it; for He is aſſured of Her Fidelity long ago, <hi>Therefore She need not Learn of Her Catholick Neighbours,</hi> for ſhe is able to Teach the World Loyalty to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And as for the <hi>Kings Perſwaſions,</hi> he hath Manifeſted to the World, <hi>He is a Chriſtian Catholick,</hi> and no <hi>Roman Catholick; for he doth not Tie up Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch a Narrow Compaſs,</hi> as to think none are Chriſtians but thoſe that owns <hi>Rome;</hi> and He hath declar'd, <hi>That it hath always been His Opinion, and that His Majeſty calls God to Witneſs:</hi> And as for <hi>Your Complaint of</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>That He would not own nor Succour you;</hi> He is not to be blam'd for that, for was not the Factious Party ſo <hi>ſet againſt Him, that they were ready to devour Him for Your ſakes?</hi> And for <hi>Your Beaſt, That you Expoſed your Lives and Fortunes in the Kings Service,</hi> it would have been better for Him if you had not been ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; you ſay, <hi>You took great Pains in Perſwading to Loyalty</hi> I do not know what you did for the Father, but <hi>I</hi> am ſure you did it not for the Son: And for <hi>You to Examine the Behaviour of the Church, Is it not known to the World that they both Periſhed Together?</hi> And the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were in good hopes They ſhould never riſe no more; but (contrary to all the Expectations of ſuch as you) God hath given them <hi>A Bleſſed Reſurrection:</hi> And who ſhould His Sacred Majeſty be Kind to (when He Entered the Throne of His Brother) but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who ſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Gap, when you did not dare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? You ſay, <hi>The Kings Promiſe did Elevate our Spirits;</hi> And well it might, for is not the Favour of a King Life? And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f we did Droop, it was not that we Feared our Prince, <hi>But Such as You, as Counts Us Hereticks:</hi> You ſay, <hi>It was never known that the King did break his Word;</hi> but it is no God-a-mercy to you; and now <hi>You think you ſhould be Happy if the Teſt and Penal Laws were Taken Away,</hi> but I hope the <hi>King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſatisfie your Deſires;</hi> for though His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty doth not make uſe of them, <hi>They may ſtand as Rods doth upon Mantle-Trees,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103998:6"/>to keep Rebellious Children in Subjection.</hi> What have you done for the King that He ſhould ſo much admire you? I am ſure he hath been a great Sufferer for you, and why ſhould you Condemn the Power of our Church for Chaſtizing Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, when God never Eſtabliſhed a Church without it; for did not God give the Children of Iſrael Laws in all Things, and thoſe that would not ſubmit to them, was to be ſeverely Puniſhed; <hi>and if any did ſecretly Intice to ſerve other Gods, They were to be ſtoned to Death:</hi> And as for the Death of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> that you ſo much complain of, were not the Laws of God and Man againſt Them? But what do you make ſo much Complaint for, hath not the King Pardoned every Body, that all ſhould be Quiet? And <hi>I</hi> would not have any one think that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not worthy to obtain the Affections of Her So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, becauſe ſhe will not comply to you: For God knows ſhe is no <hi>Snake,</hi> and therefore the King may Truſt her, and She needs no <hi>New Article;</hi> and <hi>were not you</hi> aſhamed to ſay, <hi>That One Article of Loyalty was more than the Thirty Nine, <hi>You are a Goodly Chriſtian:</hi>
               </hi> And as for <hi>Your Parliament you boaſt on; <hi>That will not ſo eaſily Admit a New Article into Their Creed:</hi>
               </hi> They may be ſuch (for ought I know) that will not own any like them that will own Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>but diſobey Him in the Chief of His Commands:</hi> But is this your Love? You ought rather to have ſtudied the Peace of his Kingdoms, but you would hurry all into Confuſion, and then Laugh at us when you have done. Do you think we value the King and Government at ſo ſmall a Rate, as to reſign up our Intereſt to ſuch as you? No, we value that above the World, and therefore do not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them that are not free to Abrogate the <hi>Teſt;</hi> for if they be, I think they do not Love His Majeſty, or is not willing to ſerve him; for the <hi>Teſt</hi> is only an Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they might Serve Him: and as long as <hi>They are Juſt and Honeſt,</hi> I know none more fit; for they have been True to their King, and I hope they will be ſo to their God, for I am ſure Gods beſt Servants, are the Kings Beſt Subjects: and as for <hi>Your Opinion which is Spread through Chriſtendom, <hi>Is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Truth of it;</hi>
               </hi> for Chriſt ſays, <hi>My Flock is but a little one, and many are Called, but few are Choſen:</hi> And as for the <hi>Corporal Preſence of Chriſt,</hi> which you count is his <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> is a Clear Miſtake to think that any of the Divines of the Reformed Church do own; for <hi>Chriſt cannot eat Himſelf,</hi> but for <hi>His Divine Preſence,</hi> God forbid any own ſhould diſown; for Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>That where two or three were gathered together, he would be in the midſt of them,</hi> and how much more at the <hi>Adminiſtration of His Bleſſed Sacrament, which Repreſents His Death.</hi> None diſowns, but that (by Faith) <hi>it is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> but as for <hi>His Natural Body it is in the Heavens,</hi> and there to be Reſerv'd till the Diſſolution: Therefore <hi>It cannot be broken nor eaten.</hi> And as <hi>for the Gravity of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England: <hi>That She is fond of any New Point of Faith,</hi> and that you ſay her own Children blames her. Alaſs, they do not underſtand the Subtilty of the <hi>Spiritual and Temporal Adverſary,</hi> for God would not allow a Similitude of His own Preſence, for God ſays, <hi>What will you liken me to?</hi> And when <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Died, did not God hide him, and was it not becauſe the People was naturally Inclin'd to <hi>Idolatry?</hi> And doth He not fill the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103998:7"/>Heavens and the Earth, and is He not in all Things elſe, and where was He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Heavens were made? Is He not Almighty, and His being is in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and who can conceive Him? For when He moves the Angels flee, and the Cherubims cover their Faces? For who is able to behold His Glory? What then will become of ſinful man, ſince God is ſo Glorious that none can ſtand before him, if <hi>Chriſt had not took Humanity upon Him,</hi> and thereby made us partakers of <hi>His Divine Nature, that we might be capable to partake of His Glory, in his Eternal Kingdom?</hi> Therefore you that are Enemies to Chriſt and his Saints, I would intreat you (if ever you intend to be happy) to Repent, and do not be overmuch Conceited of <hi>Your Infallibillity; for you ſee the Jews were Miſtaken,</hi> and do you think to be more <hi>Infallible</hi> than they that God planted with Miracles, which he never did yours? I know there is nothing Infallible but <hi>God and His Eternal Word,</hi> and I do really believe the Gates of <hi>Hell ſhall not prevail againſt His True Church,</hi> but is it any Argument that you muſt be that, becauſe you have a Being in the World, and don't you know ſome may Die and yet Live, and the Fallen Angels were not deſtroyed, for God prepared a place for them; for there is nothing comes by Chance, for Gods Providence takes Care of all, and God will be Glorified of all. Therefore I would not have you to be deceived, but to Believe, for God tells you, <hi>That Soul that ſins ſhall die,</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>That he ſhall go into Purgatory,</hi> and that ſome Men of your Order <hi>ſhould Puniſh it, and when you think it is enough, a good ſum of Money will ſend it to Heaven.</hi> Doth not this Rob God of <hi>His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> And whereas He hath commanded,</hi> that there ſhould be no other Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Himſelf,</hi> doth not it make many? <hi>For there is none hath power over the Soul but God, for is it not His own Breath?</hi> But pray tell me where this place is, and which way they go to it, <hi>and who it is that keeps the Liſt of every Mans ſins?</hi> For certainly you muſt ſend ſome Truſty Meſſenger that muſt bring the Laſt of their Iniquities ſafe, for elſe every ſin will not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, and how do you know when they are, and who is he that can tell how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſins a man commits, for they are very cunning and may not confeſs all? And there be ſome things that Men count ſin, which God may not, and ſome things which Men count not; how can you diſtinguiſh. I am very Inquiſitive to know becauſe I lov'd my late Soveraign, and I highly condemn you for your Unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for if you had had any Charity, you could not have let him ſtaid ſo long; but I hope God will deliver my Soveraign (that how is) that He ſhall never come under ſuch Dominion. You ſtole away my Soveraign, and yet are not you Contented? Methinks this ſhould have made you New Creatures, the Favour of ſuch a Prince. But what diſturbs you that you ſhould be ſo Angry with us? What doth the Sun ſhine too bright upon you? Or doth God ſhew you too much Favour? Or have you got the Nature of the Fallen Angels, that did not know when they were Happy, or hath <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> left his Spirit for a Legacy, that you may carry on his Deſigns? Do not Diſturb the Kings Peace, but reſt Contented, <hi>leſt God Clips your Wings, and if you Fall, I hope you will have no more Reſurections in this part of the World.</hi> And tho others may prompt you, to be an Enemy to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yet their Fall would be <hi>your Ruin. But God be Thanked we have no need to Fear, for the King will not with-draw his Favour from us, neither ſhall <hi>Men or Devils prevent it.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <closer>And ſo GOD Save the KING.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103998:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
